[SPEAKER_00]: So, we can do a few more excerpts from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're covering a wider range of topics.
[SPEAKER_00]: I haven't specifically selected them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we'll see how far we can get without making it too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine because a lake of water was disturbed, stirred up, became muddy.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that place, a man with eyes standing on the bank would not see the oyster shells, the gravel, the pebbles and the shoals of fish wandering around and standing still.
[SPEAKER_00]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the disturbance of the water,
[SPEAKER_00]: In just this way, bhikkhus, that the bhikkhu with disturbed mind will know his own welfare, or welfare of another, or welfare of both, or that he will realize the truly, genuinely noble attainment, knowledge and vision, which is beyond human phenomena, that is impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because bhikkhus of his disturbance of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the thing to note here is that the disturbance of the mind is something that the bhikkhu is responsible for, or anyone, everyone is responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, similarly, the muddy water, it's not that something else disturbs your mind, because of which you don't get to see the oyster shells, the gravel, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you disturb your mind on account of something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if the disturbance of the mind were truly rooted outside of yourself, if it's not up to you, well, you wouldn't be able to then overcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you cannot possibly prevent water from being disturbed, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: These things are not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sight, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, they come your way, you cannot prevent that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can train the mind to not be disturbed on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what this, what this line pretty much says, it's for an untrained mind, there will be disturbance when met with disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, because of that disturbance, you will not know what's good for you, what's good for the others, what's good for both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or that you would be able to truly realize the genuine noble attainment, knowledge and vision that's beyond the human phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, consequently, eh... 146 Aṅgatharini Kāyā says that
[SPEAKER_00]: The lake was transparent, clear and undisturbed.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that place, a man with eyes standing on the bank would see the oyster shells, the gravel, and so on, because of the non-disturbance of the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, his mind has been trained.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no disturbance amidst things that would disturb you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... that's why you will not lose the context, you will not lose the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: On what's good for you, on your own welfare, on what's beneficial for you, what's beneficial for others, what's beneficial for both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we have Anguttara 148.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is because I do not see one other thing that is quickly changing as the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So much so, because it's not easy to compare this quickly changing mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's nothing... there's no similarity we're given to how quickly the mind changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, I'm going to the 151 and 152.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because this mind... this mind is shining or luminous, as some other translations are,
[SPEAKER_00]: This mind is shining and it is defiled by the superimposed defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: The uninstructed ordinary person does not know this as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, I say, for the uninstructed ordinary person there is no development of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... we have a whole essay on this called, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The Infinity of the Mind, if I remember correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on our website.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can find it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... in brief, the point is that, eh... the mind, as in, the aspect of your experience as a whole...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the experience as a whole is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you can say... statement that there's nothing outside of it, is that which you can know only on account of your five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even that's within.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing that the mind is part of, basically, that structure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's part of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means that they cannot truly be affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the defilements cannot defile the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha meant in other suttas, where he said that upādāna, holding or attachment, whatever you want to translate it, assumption, we translate this assumption, is not the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not part of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that you... like when you practice the dhamma, you remove parts of the aggregates that were corrupted and defiled, and then you keep the rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the aggregates are not defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot be in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as the Buddha said, desire and lust in regard to the five aggregates makes upādāna be there, pretty much, in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of superimposed over them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's meant ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha said avijjā, ignorance is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means there was no first point before which aggregates were fine and then aggregates became ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance became part of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can measure the first point of origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no such point because ignorance is not in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pretty much your attitude in regard to the five aggregates, in regard to experience the whole, in regard to the whole world and realms and devas and whatever else you might be experiencing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your attitude in regard to it, fueled by desire and lust, that ignorance is there, that upādāna is there, that these superimposed defilements are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not recognizing
[SPEAKER_00]: where those defilements are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not recognizing what the problem is, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not recognizing that defilements are not in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will then be dealing with the aggregates, looking after the aggregates, trying to get rid of the aggregates, thinking that's how you're dealing with the defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what Buddha means here.
[SPEAKER_00]: The uninstructed, ordinary person doesn't understand this as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, there is no development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what is the development of the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's freeing the mind from the defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to free your mind from defilements, you need to know where the defilements are, so to speak, what they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't know what they are, you will not be able to uproot them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the statement that this mind is luminous or shining, is basically a statement of that factual impossibility to be polluted in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that you are free from pollution in regard to your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the sole point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes people, obviously,
[SPEAKER_00]: Those who haven't understood what defilements are, would then jump to conclusions and say, ah, so the mind is always pure, thus implicitly saying, I don't need to do any work because the purity is always there and it cannot be defiled.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the possibility for purity is always there, because there are certain things that cannot be defiled, such as mind, such as the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean that your experience as a whole, as in your attitude towards your own mind, towards your own aggregates, is free from defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where the defilements are, and that's where they need to be uprooted from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, Anguttara 152 says, See, they superimpose the gratuitous, because they cannot be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uninstructed worldly, not knowing,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he assumes them there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we translate the upādāna as assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Holding implies you kind of holding on to something, then you see that you're holding it, then you choose to let it go.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's far more subtle than that, upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upādāna is assumption of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: You assume something to be
[SPEAKER_00]: To be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You assume something to be, when that isn't so.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you cannot... Like, if you become aware of upādāna, if you become aware of your assumptions, they cease to be assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they require a layer of unawareness, which is the layer of ignorance, as a necessary basis for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you recognize that desire and lust are completely gratuitous, they cannot penetrate the sense objects, cannot enter them, cannot consume them, cannot partake in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, it's just this superimposed assumption over your senses, sense objects,
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on, that because it's not checked, it's not restrained, has resulted in the views that are fueled by greed, aversion, delusion, desire, and craving, and maintenance of that assumed state.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why even sensuality is one of the assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not really in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, defilements are not in the mind, or in the aggregates, or in the feeling, or in the perception, or in the form.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in regard to them, because of your unchecked attitude and desire and lust towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the one who has understood that, for him, the Buddha says, there is the development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically, if you haven't understood this, if you haven't developed the right view, there is no development of the mind, regardless of the amount of effort you put in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what these short lines so succinctly say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, I say, for the uninstructed noble disciple, there is development of the mind, because he knows it as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understood that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, on a slightly different note now, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to the one... book of one and... 130 to 139.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus... whatever bhikkhus explain
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-dhamma is dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those bhikkhus are practicing for the harm of many people, for the unhappiness of many, for the non-welfare, for the harm, for the suffering of many devas and humans.
[SPEAKER_00]: And bhikkhus, those bhikkhus produce much demerit and cause this good dhamma to disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, whatever bhikkhus explain dhamma as non-dhamma, those bhikkhus are practicing for the harm of many, for the unhappiness, for non-welfare and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for bhikkhus who explain non-vinaya as vinaya
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus who explain things not said and uttered by Tathāgata, as having been said and uttered by Tathāgata, and having been said and uttered by Tathāgata, as not having been said and uttered by Tathāgata.
[SPEAKER_00]: What has not been practiced by Tathāgata, as having been practiced by Tathāgata, and has been practiced by Tathāgata, as having not been practiced by Tathāgata.
[SPEAKER_00]: What has not been made known by Tathāgata, as having been made known, and what has been made known, as having not been made known.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing to note here is that, see, like, you would read this passage and you would kind of think, oh, yeah, you know, some people might choose to do that, but this is... this does not specify
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, it's not a requirement, it must be done consciously, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, in good faith, you might be... well, you might be thinking it's in good faith, you might be teaching the dhamma, but because you haven't understood it, you haven't understood what the dhamma is, you don't have the right view,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you're teaching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if accidentally you're misrepresenting it, which you would be without the right view, you are... it's going to result in harm and non-welfare and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's important thing to keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like if you, like, you know, express your view on what dhamma is and clearly state, oh, this is how I understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know for myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But another thing is to teach the dhamma while you know you don't know it, but you assume that simply by having a good intention to help others, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the big problem here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when those people hear that is dhamma, they'll think that's what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, they will not look for what the actual dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even your well-wishing intention to teach the dhamma to somebody,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being sure whether it's the dhamma you're teaching, or just believing that it's the dhamma you're teaching, but having verified it for yourself, that would be the sole reason for blocking their progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they'll pass away, and who knows where they're going to be reborn, and so on, and it was all... and they had a chance to approach the dhamma rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on account of your well-wishing, misguided instruction, you led them astray, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same goes for anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why even in other suttas, when you read, you know, like the sati, sanam, the fisherman, you know, the pernicious wrong view that sensuality is... there's no harm in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like that there were these morons or idiots who just had this view obstinately against the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: They genuinely had that view, could not see anything wrong with it, and they thought it's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: They thought they're practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: They thought that's what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: They thought it's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they heard that the Buddha said the opposite
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's easy to assume like there were this caricature of people, but they were most likely not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize that whenever Bhikkhus explain non-dhamma as dhamma, it doesn't need to be done with this evil intent behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It simply states, if you explain non-dhamma as dhamma, that's why you're incurring harm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter why you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it matters, the Buddha would have said so in this very sutta.